Times are a little tougher these days.
>> Who came up with this idea?
>> 3 billion dollars. I gave away all my
ether to my secretaries, 293,000 ether.
You see like the the
hyper-corporatization of the world where
these big trillion-dollar companies are
basically connecting all the resources
of the world together and they have
total control over all of it. So, your
ability to succeed or fail is not where
you're born, what language you speak,
the merit. It just basically are you
friends with [music] a small oligarchy
of people or not. People are waking up
to that. What I want to do is create a
world where we can trust each other.
Anything that improves trust in
individuals, commercial outcomes, or
institutions, this intrinsically makes
the world a fundamentally better place.
They've entered the space. They went
from trying to kill us under the Biden
administration to embracing us and I see
the writing on the wall is this embrace
and extinguish. The elites are only
elite as long as we allow them to be
elite. When you look at the AI
revolution, it's going to unemploy
within America in the next 20 years
probably over 100 million people. You
got Elon Musk saying that Tesla's no
longer going to be a car company and
he's going to build armies of robots and
you got all these AI companies where
every version of Claude is putting
structurally engineer after engineer out
of business. Well, if you extrapolate
that across the entire economy for the
knowledge workers and the blue collar
workers, every still have a 40-50%
unemployment rate. Do you think like
half of America is just going to be
sitting at home unemployed getting UBI
being happy saying everything's great?
They're just going to have a
Yeah, they're going to have a revolution
and they're going to tear down the
economic system and build another system
because they're not going to tolerate
five trillionaires, an army of robots,
and no one has anything and we're
scraping [music] by. Why would you
create this world so that you can go and
buy a private jet?
>> But throughout human history, it's
everyone for themselves. They want to
benefit themselves. You can't change
that.
Oh my god, this is
so awkward.
Today we have Charles Hoskinson. He is
the CEO and founder of Input Output.
Also, he is in a McDonald's suit.
Um
the company behind Cardano and also the
co-founder of Ethereum. Yeah, yeah.
Times are a little tougher these days
and so we all have to pick up work where
we can find it. Who came up with this
idea? This is genius.
>> [laughter]
>> I had some fun.
Uh you know, the headlines came out cuz
I told people my losses. I lost $3
billion over the last 5 years. And they
said and then so I started seeing memes
of me in a McDonald's costume and I was
running around Japan for our Japan tour
for midnight. And I said it'd be a lot
of fun to actually have a McDonald's
uniform made. And so, you know, Hong
Kong's the city of tailors. So, they
they were able to put this together in
about a day.
Were you wearing this in Japan as well?
No, no, no.
>> Oh, just for this? I kept it just for
this event, you know, it's like a
surprise keynote.
This could be the best meme ever.
>> [laughter]
>> I I think there's already a meme coin
that's been created. Oh, really?
>> Yeah.
Oh, this? Probably. Hm, okay.
>> surprise me. It's either on snakedotfund
or pumpeddotfund. What is driving you?
Why do you do what you do?
Well, I mean, I've been in the industry
before there was any money in the
industry. So, it had to be philosophical
cuz you couldn't make a living in it.
You know, I joined in 2010 and that was
part of the slashdot revolution. So,
there was a slashdot article and you we
all just kind of came in. Bitcoin was
basically a dollar and we were really
interested in in this idea of being our
own bank, owning our own money and, you
know, having some control and agency
over the digital world. If you look at
how the whole digital world works
step-by-step,
there's all these middlemen and
intermediaries that have total control
over your experience on the internet.
The search engines, the data
aggregators, the data brokers. And in
the financial world, it's much the same,
you know, you have a bank account and
any moment it could be shut down, it
could be reversed. A lot of my friends I
grew up in Colorado
were in the marijuana industry and, you
know, they live in a cash economy. They
can't get bank accounts. They're
completely unbanked.
So, to me, it just made sense to say
that money should be like the internet.
It should be open and free and there
should be a system that's like email for
money. You click a button and you just
send it to people, they get it. It's
irreversible, it's timestamped. So, that
kind of created a a love of of this idea
of Bitcoin. And at the same time, I was
also a political firebrand. I was part
of the Ron Paul campaign. He's a
conservative politician in the United
States, but he was a libertarian and he
believed in gold backed money and you
know, humble foreign policy and all this
other stuff. So, I'd read all these
books on Austrian economics and you
know, uh and and idea of having
deflationary monetary systems. So, you
have like cryptography and Cypherpunk
and the old school deflationary monetary
policy and then this libertarian core of
everybody can just do what they want to
do and like push power to the edges. And
Bitcoin was kind of the perfect
revolution for all those things. So,
then I kind of grew up in that space and
so I started Bitcoin education project
and then I created the first algorithmic
stablecoin and DEX with Dan Larimer. It
was called BitShares and it was way
ahead of its time. Then we created
Ethereum and you know, brought smart
contracts in the space and then we
created Cardano and now I got Midnight.
And despite the fact it's been 15 years,
um I stay because we're making forward
progress. You know, we have 550 million
people in the space and we actually do
have a tech stack that's going to give
us the ability to bank the unbanked and
to make everybody their their own
financial stack and it's become even
more necessary because of the AI
revolution and more necessary because
the consequences of globalism than it
was when I started in 2010. A lot of
things that we were talking about like,
oh they're hypothetical and if you allow
it will never happen. Well, I can
actually it did happen. The whole world
got shut down with a lockdown and uh you
know, then social media came and people
started getting deplatformed. You could
be this incredible influencer with
millions of fans and then Google can
just push a button and or Facebook can
push a button and you lose all of them
and you've been disintermediated from
your relationship as we saw a lot of
people
during COVID when that happened. Uh and
then you see like the the hyper
corporatization of the world where these
big trillion-dollar companies are
basically connecting all the resources
of the world together and they have
total control over all of it. So, your
ability to succeed or fail is not where
you're born, what language you speak,
the merit. It just basically are you
friends with a small oligarchy of people
or not? So, people are waking up to that
and they're saying we need to do
something about it. And you know, crypto
is the only option for these types of
things. So, that's why I do what I do. I
have made billions, lost billions. I've
been to 75 countries. I've met kings and
regular people in the trenches, farmers
in Ethiopia. It didn't really matter.
The passion's still there and the
excitement's still there. And every year
the technology gets better and we get
closer and closer to that shining city
on a hill. When you first started, was
there a personal story that made you
care about this issue? Cuz a lot of
people know about this. They don't care.
Well, one I used to eat at this one
restaurant and the gal who was the
waitress was here illegally and her
husband was here illegally. And you
know, one day she came in crying and I
said, "Well, what's wrong?" And she said
her husband was just robbed by the
police. And I said, "What What do you
mean?" And so, he was a drywaller and
he'd done a month worth of work. He got
paid in cash and he got pulled over by
police officers and they just simply
took the cash. It's called civil asset
forfeiture.
And that's basically legal theft. It
happens. There's billions of dollars a
year in civil asset forfeiture. So, I
was younger and I was like, "That That
can't be illegal." And I looked into it.
I was It was surprisingly huge thing. I
said, "Police officers are pulling over
a drywaller and just straight up taking
his money in the United States of
America. This is not like the you know,
Soviet Union or something like that or
North Korea. This is America. Shouldn't
happen." So, you you see stuff like
that, the 2008 financial collapse and
you know, none of the bankers went to
jail. Obama got elected. He said, "Hope
and change. We're going to do it." And
then he put the bank bankers in charge
and too big to fail got bigger. And also
just the increase of the debt. You know,
when I started college, you know, the US
national debt was about 4 and 1/2
trillion dollars. It was quite big, but
it was going down.
And then now it's 38 trillion dollars,
but every generation of my life, every
era of my life, it keeps going up and up
and up and up. Global debt's 233
trillion. And so I look at those things
I said there's just no way this is
sustainable. And I see the real life
consequences cuz I know a lot of people
that are now retired and I watched how
they lived their life and how they saved
and they they they really did everything
you were supposed to do and now half of
the retirement's been wiped out. Not the
number went down or anything, it's just
the buying power went down because
inflation. Uh so those are the types of
things that give me a great passion. It
says the financial systems are morally
bankrupt and wrong
and we need to correct and change that.
So I said all right, well, the only way
we can do it is build our own money. You
know, we keep being promised every year
elect this person or do this thing or
put this person in power and they'll
take care of us and it's like at what
point do we realize that it's all a lie?
You know, they'll never take care of us
cuz they always just become part of the
system. They go they say don't be evil
and then they just remove that mission
statement. The only way you can
constrain people is to go to can't be
evil. You have to build systems that by
their construction have integrity within
them.
And if you do that, then you start
getting trust, truth and honesty again.
So, you know, small formative
experiences they accumulate up and the
more you travel, the more confirmation
cuz everywhere you look you find the
pockets of corruption. Everywhere you
look you find the laws that don't make
sense and every industry's got some
major problem whether it be my clinic
cuz I run a health care business as
well. We have 18,000 patients and
dealing with insurance companies and
billing
or it be work that we do and I have a
bison ranch and just dealing with the
price of hay. You know, there's always
some nepotism and corruption where you
you look for it and you say I just want
to live in a world of like fairness and
one common set of rules and everybody
has to play by them and I can verify the
things that people are telling me are
true and that's the promise of
blockchain. That sounds like a system
level problem.
and misaligned incentives. You talked
about that, too. But, if you want to
design a new system, how do you make
sure that the new designer won't
misalign? Yeah. Yeah. Well, that's the
power of self-evolving systems. You
know, you're never going to get it right
initially, but the question is can the
system, like biological systems, adapt
and change so that the original intent
of the system is preserved? Uh so,
cryptocurrencies are phenomenal example
of that. They're built to be
antifragile. So, they get hit, you know,
you know, when I was growing up in the
industry, Mount Gox was always a big
existential question. It's one of the
reasons we created BitShares cuz they
said, "Oh god, you know, we're going to
have a situation where somebody who
trades 80% of all the Bitcoin volume is
going to collapse. If that does, I guess
Bitcoin's dead." And yet, not only did
the system survive that, it thrived and
grew and became better because the
social dynamics were built in a way that
the system was antifragile. So, there's
certain design principles in complex
adaptive systems that you can put in
that create those properties. The second
thing is you have to be very good at
competition. The reason why a lot of
these things are bad in life is they get
monopolies or oligarchies and you can't
displace them or fire them, you know?
And that can be with political parties
or you know, that can be with economic
systems, that can be with technology.
You know, when Microsoft was king of the
world in the '90s and early 2000s, tech
got very stagnant because everything was
about preserving and protecting the
monopoly of Microsoft as opposed to
innovation. And then other people came,
they they competed, they built new
things, and suddenly Microsoft said, "Oh
my gosh, we have to actually innovate
again or else we're going to die as a
company." Uh so, competitive equilibria
are really important as well. Not only
do you have antifragility, but you have
many different standards and you let
them fight each other. So, Ethereum
makes Cardano better, Cardano makes
Ethereum better, Midnight makes the rest
of these guys better. We all bring
something new and different to the
table, and by doing that, what that
provides is a basis upon which we can
evolve. And third is community
participation. You have to have
participatory governance. If people are
civically involved and they have
incentives to be involved, they have
ownership in the system. It's called the
IKEA effect. You know, if you buy
something from IKEA, you build it, you
tend not to throw it away, even though
it's not very good, because you built
it. You know, it's like, "Ah, I can't
throw that." I had a friend who built a
couch and he's like, "I can't throw that
away." It's like, "You've had it for 30
years." I don't care, man. I got
I built that thing. I like got cuts on
my hand and everything. Uh so, people
feel a lot of value in a system if they
feel ownership and equity inside that
system. When you look at a lot of failed
political systems, there's this us
versus them or otherism, where I didn't
build that system, I'm not connected to
that system, and therefore the system's
evil and wrong, but I have no
accountability, responsibility, or
connection. Cryptocurrencies are
intrinsically participatory. What makes
Cardano great isn't me, it's that we
have a decentralized government. We have
dReps and a constitution, and we have
constitutional amendments and all these
things, and a budget process that's
participatory. And people in more than
100 countries participate. So, every
single person says, "I built part of
Cardano. I'm part of this ecosystem."
And that's what makes it strong. And
then you end up getting a wisdom of the
crowds effect, where bad ideas, they
tend to fizzle out over time,
and good ideas, they tend to get
stronger over time. And then eventually
you adopt that. And I'd say the fourth
thing is you have to be merciless about
product market fit. You have to say,
"Wait, what problems are we actually
trying to solve?" You tell a consumer
you're going to do X, but you actually
do Y,
then they start burning out a little
bit. That's the issue the cryptocurrency
space is having right now. We went
promised that we're revolutionaries and
we're going to change the entire world,
and instead we got dog with hat.
You know, and so we had meme coin mania
and the NFT mania and all this other
stuff, and people say, "Well, that's
great, but what you've done is you've
just created this magic
engine to over financialize all things.
Everything becomes a token. Everything
becomes a prediction market. In fact, I
just delivered a keynote with this
McDonald's uniform on. As soon as I was
leaving, Snack Down Fund, somebody
launched a meme coin of of me with the
uniform on. It's already a hundred
thousand dollar market cap. So, it just
shows you like what we do as an
ecosystem. And when retail investors and
retail holders are told, "Wait a minute,
you're this is supposed to be
revolutionary and change the world."
Yeah. They don't feel that meaningful
connection to it. So, the narrative
becomes bankrupt. So, you have to have
product market fit and narrative
consistency within the system, and
people have to see and feel the power
and value that the system provides. Now,
certain jurisdictions already feel this.
I have employees in Argentina. We have a
lovely big office in Buenos Aires. It's
a wonderful place to be. Uh and they
refuse to be paid in the peso. They want
to be paid in cryptocurrencies. I've
I've paid them for years in it. There's
a hundred billion dollars in
cryptocurrencies in Argentina, and their
economy's only seven hundred billion.
So, one out of every seven dollars is in
crypto, and they're probably going to be
one of the first countries with private
money uh because of the directionality
there. So, why do they do that? Because
if they hold the peso, they lose twenty
percent of their value a month. If they
hold crypto, it stays stable. Even
Bitcoin is a lot more stable than uh
than the peso.
>> Definitely. So, it makes perfect sense
for them to actually create a parallel
economy and do these types of things. Uh
so, you have to find those product
market fits. And when and when you can
do that with good governance, and you
can do that with competitive equilibria,
and you can do that with the right
founding principles and the
antifragility, you can build systems
that over time, they conquer the world
regardless of uh particular person dies
or a law's passed or any of these things
cuz they're just simply stronger than
any of the current governance systems we
have. You know, when when I try to
express or explain what blockchains are
to beginners, I use this analogy of
highway, right? But, it seems like
Cardano and what you're building is so
much bigger than that.
Correct me if I'm wrong. Is it an
infrastructure? Yeah, what I want to do
is create a world where we can trust
each other. I don't think people really
understand the the the negative
consequences of a lack of trust.
So, I'll give you an example. I own a
ranch in Wyoming and every now and then
I buy some of the neighbors cuz I need
to build a road or my bison need grazing
or whatever. So, let's say I like the
neighbor and have a good relationship
with him. And I go to say, "Hey, I need
to buy part of your ranch." All right,
all right, come on over and you know,
bring a bottle of whiskey, you get
shit-faced drunk, and you talk about it,
and then you shake hands, and then you
you have a deal, and then maybe a month
into it you find out his brother owns
part of it, and like he didn't have
permission or whatever. So, you bring
the brother together, you get shit-faced
drunk again, and you figure it out. And
then after two meetings, two two
drinking sessions, you figured it out,
you buy the land, you're done. That's
the transaction. That's a trusted
transaction. Now, let's play the
counterfactual. Let's say I don't like
the brother. I don't like him. Okay, I
come in I don't talk to him. My lawyer
calls him up. My lawyer talks to his
lawyer. They hardball negotiate for 2 3
months. We sign a deal, turns out the
brother owns part of it. Well, I feel
screwed in that. So, what happens? I
litigate. So, then we have 2 years of
lawsuits, and we're going back and
forth, and then eventually I win, and I
get the land. It's the same outcome. I
got the land. The difference is lots of
money, lots of time, and a lot of
heartache. And the only delta between
the two is trust in that relationship.
Do you trust the person not trust the
person? So, anything that improves trust
in individuals, commercial outcomes, or
institutions, this intrinsically makes
the world a fundamentally better place.
And really what blockchain's about is
restoring trust in commerce at its core.
You know, when you think about Bitcoin
or what have you, the first use case of
Bitcoin was irreversibility, no
chargebacks. When you're at e-commerce,
you're a merchant buying stuff online,
all the time you have people with credit
card fraud or all these other issues.
They buy you think you have the money it
turns out with stolen credit card or
it's a chargeback or something like
that. With Bitcoin I get it it's mine. I
can't reverse it. So already it was a
intrinsically superior from an
e-commerce viewpoint than than credit
cards were. So suddenly I can trust it.
I don't care if you bought it and you
live in Uganda. I don't care if you
bought it and you live in Argentina.
It's like cash. You've already paid me.
I've actually received the full amount.
There's no fraud or risk in this
transaction. I've been paid. So I can
trust you now in ways I couldn't trust
you before. And then as you look at the
evolution of feel as we went to the
second and third generation now into the
fourth generation, what we're doing is
broadening the scope of things that I
can trust you with. In fact, the most
exciting part what Midnight's working on
right now
is this concept of selective disclosure.
So you say, "Okay,
we overshare. You know, we come in and
you say, "All right, I need to do
business with you. Are you a credit
investor or not? Are you a US resident
or not? Or you know, is this pre-tax or
post-tax money?" Or whatever the heck
the questions are. Ordinarily how I
prove that is I give you all these
documents that are very revealing. I
give you my passport. I give you my
financial records. I give you residency
information. You didn't ask that
question. You just asked, "Are you part
of this group or this group? Are you in
the group or out of the group?" It's a
yes-no question. So that the minimum
viable disclosure is just a
zero-knowledge proof. So in a global
system if you could move to a selective
disclosure system, then all of a sudden
I can do business with pretty much
anyone anywhere. I collect almost no
information about those people and yet I
fully trust them inside that
relationship. And I know that it's a low
fraud issue. I know it's a safe
transaction. Settlement's compliance.
I'm not going to have a lawsuit over it.
I'm not going to have a regulatory
event. Well, that means that commerce
can travel at the speed of thought which
is that email for money idea that we
had. Well, if it works at the individual
level, it works at the business level.
Toyota would love to work with Chinese
car companies. They run at 1/3 the cost,
they have armies of brilliant engineers,
they're growing exponentially. So, if
they collaborate on technology and
market, they could make billions of
dollars. But, how does Toyota trust that
Chinese car company not going to steal
their software or their logistics chains
or these other things? What recourse do
they have if they do? So, they can't get
there, so that collaboration is
difficult, and the failure of that
collaboration cost them billions of
dollars of potential money. And at the
nation-state
level, nation-states all the time want
to work together, like the United States
and Venezuela. There's been a change in
management. If they can find a way to
make a deal, you can open up one of the
largest oil economies in the entire
world and upgrade them from 3 billion
million barrels a day to 10 million in
production, and US oil companies can
make tens of billions of dollars. But,
we can't trust the Venezuelan
government.
>> But, how does Midnight change that?
Because it's all compositional. So, each
step of the way, it's about building up
blocks and say, "Okay, well, what
information do I share? How does dispute
resolution work? If there's a bad
outcome, how do we get restitution for
that bad outcome?" And compositionally,
you build your way up. So, Toyota and
that car company say, "Okay, I know that
if I share this data, it's going to be
kept private, and they can't steal it.
And if And I know that when I say erase
it, it's automatically erased cuz a
confidential compute cluster has it, and
it can't leave the boundary. So, the
intellectual property theft doesn't
happen. I know that when a person's
working, it's a pre-vetted employee cuz
I've already verified that that person's
trusted, and it's not some new
contractor that magically appeared from
a third-party company, and suddenly
they're getting access to all of our
documents or things like that. So, it's
It's compositionally a hard problem, but
you start at the individual level, that
same question of, you know, am I allowed
to do business with you or not? And then
you work your way up to the company
level, and then eventually you can work
your way up to the country level. And
each step of the way, you have more
privacy-enhancing technologies and more
disclosure regimes, but eventually you
get to a point where things can be
built. And what's cool is you can use a
lot of the techniques we've built in the
cryptocurrency space to create economic
certainty. Like for example, Venezuela
absolutely could go and re-nationalize
the oil fields, but you know, Ethereum
pioneered bonding and slashing. So if
they do that, what if they burn 50
billion dollars in assets? So yes, they
can seize something, but then they would
lose 50 billion in liquidity or
something like that in the process of
doing it. So then I as an investor would
say, "Well, as long as the value is
below that burn and slash amount, I feel
safe because it's not rationally not
rational for them to go and do that. I
have an insurance policy for these types
of things. Then suddenly we can trust
each other for the first time ever and
build that infrastructure for the first
time ever. So that's really what
blockchain provides is is it's a
mechanism for us to trust each other.
The first generation was about a trusted
bulletin board that what went in it was
time-stamped, immutable, and auditable,
and we created a common account amongst
everybody. It happened even though we
may hate each other and we speak
different languages and we live in
different places, we can't disagree on
the order of operation and facts. We say
this is a common history that we have.
Then we built transaction systems and
then we built programmability so you can
transact arbitrary value, and now we're
starting to get to those more
complicated things which is selective
disclosure, and then that gives us
another piece of the puzzle. Now it
takes decades and decades and
alternative governance systems and new
economics and these things to be able to
fully sort it all out, but every step of
the way you gain more and more business
you can do, and you bring more and more
customers in the type of business you
can do.
And it could be as small as a a trading
card game like the next Pokémon. I would
like some assurances that the special
cards that I get are actually special
and they're not over-printing them and
they're actually not they're they're
actually rare. I I was a beta tester for
Magic the Gathering and I had a black
lotus. I'd like to know, you know, these
these types of things.
And it can be as complicated as, uh, you
know, lithographs with a with an artist
and uh, you want to make sure that the
artist only ever produces 12 of those
lithographs or something like that. It's
the same technology stack for these
types of things. And what's so cool
about it is the smart cow effect. So,
only one person in the industry has to
solve and open source the problem.
And then once they've done that,
everyone has access to it. We solved the
blockchain trilemma with Ouroboros
Leios. Within 18 months of launching
that this year, everybody will probably
take our design or our ideas and
integrate it into their blockchain. Uh,
Vitalik and the rest of the gang, they
solved smart contracts. Now everybody
has smart contracts, right? It's not a
competitive differentiator. Time in
2014, it certainly felt that way. We
were quite happy with it. Uh, but no
longer is that the case. The same for
on-chain governance. We built this
amazing on-chain governance system as
did Tezos and Algorand, excuse me, and
uh, Polkadot for, uh, for Cardano. Uh,
but that's not a competitive
differentiator in 18 to 36 months
because people take that. Uh, so it's
it's hard for me cuz I have to keep
building to to stay relevant and
innovate, but it's great for the
industry as a whole because we all learn
from each other and grow from each other
and we find new ways to bring new
businesses in.
When you want to change the whole
system, there has to be people that, you
know, are not happy about it. For
example, uh, banks or traditional
finance were not happy about blockchain
and crypto and revolution.
Do you have that now? Like people that
don't like what you're doing? Well, I
mean, they're certainly happy. Canton is
right over there, you know, so there the
banks are coming and building their own
thing.
Everybody finds a way to make money in
it. Where I get pissed off is when they
try to change the rules to screw us.
I don't have any problem competing with
BlackRock or Goldman Sachs or JP Morgan.
What I have a problem is when they form
their own consortia then they go to the
regulator and try to change the laws to
ban non-custodial wallets and ban
the decentralized aspects and ban DeFi
and all these other things so that all
the businesses forced by law to go to
them. I think that's where the friction
points come. It has to be a fair game
and let the consumer decide, let the
experience decide, let the value decide.
It can't be a rigged game where no
matter what the consumer wants, they
basically are told or mandated for their
protection to go to a cartel that
basically has no concern about cost or
consumer protections or any of these
other things. So,
they've entered the space. They went
from trying to kill us under the Biden
administration to embracing us and I see
the writing on the wall. It's this
embrace and extinguish and we see a lot
of these bank coins and Fed coins
working their way in and their
permission consortia. You can't join
them. It's permission only and they're
using their network effect to kind of
push people through.
I think we can still win because we have
the the world on our side, but it just
makes the job a little bit harder in a
nutshell. And also these banks they
there's nothing they stand for. At the
end of the day they say, we just want to
make slightly more money and be slightly
faster. Whereas here I'm saying, hey I I
want you to be your own bank and I I
want you to be in control of your
freedom of association, commerce and
expression. I I want you to, you know,
actually live a life where you can trust
people and work well with people. I want
to give you governance systems. You can
write your own constitution and you can
collaborate with people in 100
countries. There's so much more richness
in that world than the the transaction
now is slightly faster and slightly
cheaper, but it's exactly the same. Oh,
and by the way, if the government
doesn't like you, they can push a button
and anytime shut off your money.
Like, why would you create this world so
that you can go and buy a private jet or
something like that?
>> human history, it's everyone for
themselves. They want to benefit
themselves. You can't change that, can
you? Well, but we have been. You know,
throughout human history, we created
religion and governments and all kinds
of things and we went from small tribes
and nomads to, you know, building cities
and building much more elaborate social
structures. And each generation, because
of that collaboration, it's been getting
better for people. You know, my
great-grandparents, they grew up in a
time that when you had eight kids, four
of them died before the age of 20. And
now we live in a time where it's almost
unheard of for somebody to have several
kids die. You know, we take clean
drinking water for granted, but the vast
majority of the world throughout human
history didn't have it. I once visited
some Roman ruins in England, and one of
the things that was most striking is
when they were taking a look at the
latrines where the late legionaries were
there, all of latrines were filled with
tons of parasites because all the Roman
legionaries were infected. Well, modern
medicine's there and that's a collection
of collaboration. So, I think deep down
inside, I agree with Steven Pinker and
these other people that the better angel
of our nature, we we want
to do a good job. We want to help
people. The problem is because we can't
trust people, we run into situation
where we default to the Nash equilibria
and we just become adversarial. Then we
become cynical and then we just go
tribal again and we try to find our
group and fight. So, what you do is you
defeat that with good technology and you
slowly work your way through. Like, if
we have this selective disclosure system
and it works its way through the
government, the Epstein files aren't an
issue cuz no matter what they redact,
the real names come out and they get
selectively disclosed and then you say,
"Well, yeah, that's actually verified
from the DOJ. Somebody within it leaked
it, but no one can prove it. So, you
don't have a Snowden situation. Uh they
can stay anonymous, but still reveal
these things. So, it calls truth to
power, and then you can slowly but
surely get to a more honest society. The
other thing is governance innovations
bring more people into participation.
So, we used to live in a world of strong
men and kings, and then democracy and
republics come, and you kind of have
like an elite ruling class, and then
kind of like an oligarchical finance
class, and then everyday people. So,
it's not quite democratic. Like
America's not really democratic, but at
least more people get to participate.
You can imagine this idea that a Obama
can grow up as a poor kid in Hawaii and
be the president of the United States
one day. That would have never happened
in a monarchical system.
When you have better governance systems
like a DAO system or any of these other
structures,
more and more people participate the
governance. More and more people
eventually gets much more fair and much
more balanced than a And what's cool
about the cryptocurrency space is
we're doing this in real time. That's
smart cow effect. It wasn't too long ago
that the only thing the DAO was was like
a a venture capitalist firm that was
decentralized.
And now we have new voting systems and
and we're exploring ZK quadratic voting
and soulbound tokens and preference
orderings and all kinds of cool new
things that have never seen their way.
Like in Cardano, we did liquid feedback,
liquid democracy. This was a proposal
from the Pirate Party in Sweden 20 years
ago. No one ever put it in production.
We put it in for the DRep system of
Cardano. So, a political scientist can
now look at scale for a network of 1.4
million people and say, "Wow, there's
now actually a liquid democracy system
running. What happened with it? Did it
produce a good outcome, a bad outcome,
whatever?" Well, that system can be
combined with soulbound tokens or ZK
quadratic voting or all these other
things, and then we may end up with a
situation where you get 80% voter
participation instead of 5%. So, people
are much more are
At some point, small nation states say,
"We should use that." And then larger
nation states say, "We should use that."
Corporate governance, they say, "I'm
going to build a company and that's how
I want to govern my company." And they
push through. Well, over time what that
does is it changes entirely the world.
And then when you have more
participation from the bottom,
you don't end up having these power
structures that are totally
unaccountable and they're against the
people. They they end up taking over.
The other thing is the elites are only
elite as long as we allow them to be
elite. And they tend to be fragile. And
that's why they get so violent. Um when
you look at the AI revolution, it's
going to unemploy within America in the
next 20 years probably over 100 million
people. You got Elon Musk saying that
Tesla's no longer going to be a car
company and he's going to build armies
of robots. And you got all these AI
companies where every version of Claude
is putting structurally engineer after
engineer out of business. And like 70%
of all the code being written right now
for uh Anthropic is by Anthropic's
products, not its engineers. At one
point it's going to probably be 95%. So,
that means I don't need a thousand
engineers anymore. I need 50 engineers
to do the same amount of labor. Well, if
you extrapolate that across the entire
economy for the knowledge workers and
the blue collar workers, that means
you'll have a 40-50% unemployment rate.
So, do you think like half of America's
just going to be sitting at home
unemployed getting UBI being happy
saying everything's great? Idle hands do
the govern- devil's work. They're just
going to have a They're going to have a
revolution.
>> Yeah, they're going to have a
revolution. And they're going to tear
down the economic system and build
another system because they're not going
to tolerate five trillionaires, an army
of robots, and no one has anything, and
we're scraping by. They're just not
going to do it.
>> Something Elon Musk said, uh
we do not need to save for retirement
anymore because of AI.
>> Yeah. And I it's And if you really dig
into what he's getting at, there's two
outcomes. Either you create unlimited
abundance and everybody gets the fruits
of their labors, but in a capitalist
system that doesn't happen. Or uh the
whole economic system comes collapsing
down and we're going to reset the system
and we'll move to a post-capitalist
society. So, what does that society look
like? It's probably going to be inspired
a lot by what we've learned in the
cryptocurrency space. We've experimented
with so many different things,
inflation, demurrage, universal basic
income, airdrops, this thing, that
thing. We've run real time 400 different
ways of running a central bank. And
usually when you experiment with these
things, you do it years to decades to
centuries in nation-states. We do it in
competition with tens of thousands of
different standards weeks to months. So,
the data that we have from this 550
million-person social experiment is very
significant and I do believe that we can
leverage that to rebuild the economic
order to a much more fair system and get
people where they need to be. It's just
some people look at it cynically and
they say, "Oh, nothing will change." But
I remind you that the only thing that we
know is change happens. When my
grandfather grew up, he grew up during
the Great Depression and throughout the
arc of his entire life, he witnessed the
Great Depression, World War II, he
fought in the Korean War as part of the
Frozen Chosen. He witnessed the Red
Scare and hysteria and everybody thought
we were all going to die from hydrogen
bombs. He witnessed the entire 1960s and
the cultural revolution there. He
witnessed the moon landing. He witnessed
the IT and cable revolution. He helped
invent the cable box. And then he
witnessed the personal computing
revolution. He witnessed the rise of the
internet and then he witnessed the rise
of cell phones before he died. So,
imagine that over the arc of one life
seeing all these massive
transformational changes and cultural
changes. So, there's no reason we can't
endure the same. And the difference here
is we have a lot more agency on what
comes next. You know, if we come
together with this type of technology,
we have the means and ability to build
things that not only are sustainable,
they're fair. You know, everybody gets a
seat at the table. Some small, some
large and everybody gets to feel like
they're contributing towards something
that's of mutual benefit. What you just
said is based on democracy is better.
And that, you know, the
collective gathered wisdom of human
beings
is better than a really smart leader
leading the world or the country or the
region. Yeah.
What is this idea based on? Well, the
wisdom of the crowds is a documented
event. You can see it and the caveat
isn't just the masses are better, the
incentivized masses are better. That's
really the key. So, if you're just
voting and you have no stakes in the
thing you're voting for, you're not
going to make good decisions. But, if
there are stakes and you have an upside,
you always tend to make better
decisions. If you look at Robin Hanson's
research with prediction markets or any
of the people that have studied them for
years, they almost always make better
decisions than regular everyday experts.
So, you see elections and the prediction
market tends to predict the election
better than the talking heads that are
on CNN or MSNBC or these other things.
So, what you need to do is create
democratic processes, but create the
appropriate incentives within those
processes for people to participate and
care about the outcomes. The other thing
is that you have to give breathing space
and you have to layer time and expertise
within these democratic systems. So,
where it's highly specialized, it's not
the wisdom of the crowds, rather it's
the delegation to a collection of
experts who are of adversarial views.
So, he said, "I'm going to build a
nuclear power plant." You don't ask the
group, you delegate to a committee and
that committee has the expertise
necessary and there are some for it and
there some against it and they kind of
work together to try to figure it out,
but they're sufficiently well
credentialed they can do that. What's
cool is if you layer liquid democracy
with that, you can create that system of
delegated authority. You say, "On this
particular issue, I'm not qualified to
vote. So, I'm going to give my vote to
Bob over there cuz he's a a engineer and
he's really, really skilled at this
stuff, and he's worked on nuclear power
plants for 30 years, so he's going to
have a better opinion about whether we
should build that nuclear power plant or
not. And also, I don't really fully
trust Bob, so I'm going to give 30% of
my vote to Alice, and she's an activist
and hates nuclear power plants. So, Bob
and Alice got to, you know, hammer it
out and figure this thing, and maybe
they'll come to a compromise, and if
they want to get it done, that's the
only way it's going to happen. That's
what creates good outcomes. You have to
have incentivized decision-making and
incentivized wisdom of the crowds, and
then expert systems help to AI is so
powerful because if it's used correctly,
it provides a almost monarchal-like
wisdom. You know, it has this god mode
where it can see the whole system, and
it can give you a lot of really good
advice, but it doesn't share our values.
So, while it can give us a lot of great
advice, it doesn't have the wisdom to
tell you what you ought to do or what's
good for society. It just gives you the
options, option A, B, C, D, and it can
check the options that you're looking at
and give you epistemic hygiene in that.
Are you succumbing to cognitive
fallacies and biases? Um, is the
information credible? Has the data been
checked? Oh, you know, all these basic
questions that take an enormous amount
of time.
How people kill a decision-making
process is they overcomplicate it, and
they try to kill you with information
overload. They give you too much
information. They give you too much
stuff. It's almost like when you're
dealing with a 5-year-old and they're
telling you a story, and they never get
to the point, and they just keep
babbling and babbling and babbling and
babbling, and you're just like, "Shut
the up and tell me what you're
actually asking here, okay?" Can I have
some candy? Okay, you can have the
candy, okay? I didn't need to know about
the squirrel, the tree, and the birds,
and the and the horses, and the
grasshoppers that you found, and these
other things. Well, that's modern
society is you get this information
overload. What the AI does is it helps
you filter it down. I use it every day
now for that. Like, there's all these
podcasts, and I've been on the Lex
Fridman show and the Shawn Ryan show and
all these other things, and they end up
being like 5-hour episodes. And so, I
always imagine like if I'm going to go
watch a 5-hour podcast, do I have the
time for that? Well, what if it's a dud?
I've just wasted like a work day
listening to this thing. So, what's the
first thing I do? I take the 5-hour
podcast, I put it in Gemini, and I say,
"Can you summarize everything that
happened here? Is there anything
interesting?" Then it gives me a nice
little text summary, and I read that,
and then I decide based on that summary,
do I want to engage with this podcast or
not? So, that's a great example of how
you go from a huge vast pile of raw
information to now a curated thing, and
it helps you focus and make your
decision, do I want to engage, and what
areas do I want to engage with? Like,
maybe of those 5 hours, 30 minutes was
really relevant to me and my job. So,
I'm going to focus in on just those 30
minutes and skip the other 4 and 1/2
hours of podcast. You couldn't do that
before.
>> You know what I did with the Shawn Ryan
show you went on? I did the same thing.
And there was one thing, one important
note that it puts down, and it tells me,
you said, "Time's actually slow down."
So, the perception of time.
>> Yeah.
Could you elaborate on it? Yeah, the
timing Well, that's a slightly different
time. Those are time expansion
experiences. So, there's uh I think it's
Steven Taylor who wrote the book, a
psychologist, uh who was really
interested in humans' perception of
time. So, deep within your brain, in the
limbic system, there's some regulating
functions that change your perception of
time. So, time can either be very slow,
or time can actually
move very quickly. So, you may notice
like when you're in a flow state, you're
really in the zone, you get your music
in, you do like 4 hours of work, but it
only feels like 30 minutes. Or you get
like in a car accident, time like seems
to slow down a little bit, and even
though the accident occurred over like a
2-second period, it feels like a whole
minute has been stretched out, and
you're kind of like seeing everything in
slow motion. So, that's called a time
expansion experience. And what he was
really interested in is that certain
drugs, like salvia and DMT and others,
actually can influence the time
expansion experience and give you
extraordinary time expansion. Salvia in
particular, if you take a heroic dose,
there's been accounts of people that
lived another lifetime. So, the real
clock time was only just a few minutes
of clock time, but then they report
living like years in another person's
life. There was a person in Alaska who
took because he got the extract ratios
wrong, too much of it. He collapsed on
his bathroom floor and then he woke up
in Texas in another body as another
person, married, had kids, worked at
Walmart. He's living this life for
several years and then he wakes up again
on the bathroom floor in Alaska with his
roommate and he's like, "Oh god, where
the am I? Where's my wife? Where's
my kids?"
>> Isn't that just called tripping? Yeah,
it's just crazy when you think about it,
but that's called time expansion
experience and you can experience that
on ketamine or DMT or any of these other
things cuz it affects the parts of the
brain that that are there. And there's
even people that are studying can they
tinker with time expansion for elite
operators like using transcranial
magnetic stimulation or focused
ultrasound? Can you use that to actually
like when you're a Navy SEAL group or
something like that, everybody has hyper
perception and they have bullet time
basically. So, there's some really cool
use cases here for these types of things
and I have a lot of friends that work in
that space. So, it's I kind of geek out
from time to time. Um, you've been super
successful right now. You talk about
incentives.
Is financial incentives still a thing
for you? No, it's never been.
If it was, I would have stopped a really
long time ago. I gave away all my ether
to my secretary. It was 293,000 ether.
So, I didn't know it was going to be
worth that much at the time, but you
know, it hadn't launched yet. But it's
never been a thing, you know, I've been
in Bitcoin since it was a dollar and
beyond and you know, it's gone up, it's
gone down. It's always been about the
work and the love of the work. The
biggest thing you can commit is get to
attach to lifestyle. You know, you get
attached to the jet, you get attached to
the ranch, you get attached to these
things. They're nice, they're beautiful,
they're a lot of fun. Believe me, when
you're traveling and you have a 4-hour
layover and like you get on the plane
and there's a guy farting next to you
every day and you're like, "I don't to
get out of this. Okay, this is bad.
But but at the same time it's like
that's not what defines you. What
defines you is the people you meet, the
interactions you have, the things you
build, and ultimately what you leave
behind, and the meaning you derive from
that life.
So, if you fall in love with the things
and you make your life about that, you
live a life of fear cuz you wake up
every day saying, "What if this all
disappears? What if this all disappears?
I have to make more money. I have to
make more." And then everything becomes
transactional. Every relationship, every
interaction, everything you do, you
don't look for who is this person and
try to get to know them and have empathy
from you're saying, "How can this person
benefit me? How can this interview I'm
doing right now make the price of X, Y,
and Z go up?" Instead of how do I just
have a good conversation with this
person and you know and and uh share
some wisdom and they share some wisdom
with me. So, it's it's bad to go down
that road and uh nothing good comes of
it and I know so many billionaires who
are divorced and miserable and you know,
they have just miserable lives and their
children hate them and and they say,
"Oh, look at all this money and power I
have." And I say, "Great, but your
personal life is just a
trainwreck. You know, why are you here?
Why are you doing this?" Well, you know,
that's just the nature of the game. No,
it doesn't really have to be that way.
Start with being a good person, start
with a life of meaning, and start doing
what you love. And if you make the
money, you make the money. You don't
make the money, you don't make the
money. They say, "Oh, that's easy for
you to say, Charles. You're rich." I
say, "I wasn't rich when I started.
Yeah. I was broke. You know, I I ran
Input Output the first year on $200,000
and that included everyone's salary, my
salary. I was staying at hotels where
like the bedbugs had bedbugs. Uh you
know, it was it was it was hardcore, you
know, and it was real hard and it was
and every month we had to figure out how
to make payroll and scrape by and I
lived that way for quite some time. And
yeah, we got fortunate and you know, the
markets moved to the moon, but But if it
hadn't happened, I'd still be here, you
know, and I'd still be working cuz I
love what I do and I love this idea of
being able to give everybody a system
like this.
You know, time definitely slows down
when I'm talking to you. Um I have a
gift for you.
I have a gift I have a special delivery
for [laughter] you.
Our team literally just went and buy
some McDonald's for you.
>> [laughter]
>> Well, thank you very much. Would you
like some fries with that? Yeah.
Thank you so much.
>> Yeah, this was a lot of fun.
>> Thank you.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, let's get a picture together.
Thank you.